Guide to the Tom Copeland Research Materials on Elmer Smith and the Centralia Tragedy
Special Collections, University of Washington Libraries
Tom Copeland research materials on Elmer Smith and the Centralia Tragedy
1905-1998
University of Washington Libraries Special Collections Box 352900 Seattle, WA 98195-2900
2021
2021-001
Copeland, Tom,$d1950-
1.95 cubic feet (3 boxes) plus 1 oversize vertical file
Tom Copeland’s research materials on Elmer Smith, attorney for the Industrial Workers of the World involved in the Centralia Tragedy of 1919.
Tom Copeland is the author of The Centralia Tragedy of 1919: Elmer Smith and the Wobblies and has worked in the family childcare field since 1981.
Elmer Smith, who is documented in this collection, was a progressive lawyer in Centralia, Washington who defended the Industrial Workers of the World members arrested following the Centralia Tragedy of 1919. Smith was a high school teacher before becoming an attorney. As an attorney he represented IWW members, loggers and miners. After hearing rumors of a planned attack on their IWW meeting hall, several Wobblies consulted with Smith about whether they had a right to defend themselves and their hall. Their previous hall had been attacked the year before during a parade. Smith contacted Washington’s governor and the IWW’s asked for protection from Centralia law enforcement. However, both attempts were denied as were IWW member efforts to plead for justice from town residents. Smith then advised the Wobblies it would be legal to physically defend themselves if attacked first.
On November 11th, 1919, under the guise of an Armistice Day Parade, American Legionnaires attacked the Centralia IWW hall. IWW members shot and killed four Legionnaires during the attack and wounded several others. A posse later mistakenly killed one of their own. IWW member Wesley Everest fled the scene, killing one of the men pursuing him, and was put in jail. That night,he was pulled from his cell by a group of vigilantes and lynched on a bridge above the Chehalis River. Ten men, including Smith, were arrested and tried for murder during a trial that was heavy with fear and intimidation. Seven men were found guilty and one was judged insane. Smith was acquitted and spent the rest of his life advocating for their release. He was harassed, arrested and disbarred for his work. He was reinstated before he died.
The collection is arranged in the following series and subseries:
SERIES 1: SUBJECT FILES AND RESEARCH NOTES, 1905-1998
Subseries A: Edward Coll: Letters, Pamphlets, and Newspaper
Subseries B: Elmer Smith
Subseries C: Wesley Everest and Family
Subseries D: Radio Broadcast by Eugene Barnett
Subseries E: Centralia Tragedy and Trial
Subseries F: Scholarly Papers and Manuscripts
Subseries G: Newspaper and Magazine Articles
Subseries H: Smith Family Papers
SERIES 2: CORRESPONDENCE, 1942-1995
SERIES 3: ORAL HISTORY INTERVIEW MATERIALS, 1972-1990
Subseries A: Transcripts, Notes, and Correspondence
Subseries B: Interview Audio Cassette Recordings
Subseries C: Digital Copies of Interview Transcripts and Recordings
This collection contains Tom Copeland’s research materials on Elmer Smith, attorney for the Industrial Workers of the World involved in the Centralia Tragedy of 1919. These materials were used by Copeland in the writing of his book, The Centralia Tragedy of 1919: Elmer Smith and the Wobblies (1993). Also included are research materials from his 1986 article, "Wesley Everest, IWW Martyr" published in The Pacific Northwest Quarterly. As a part of his research, Copeland conducted a series of oral history interviews with Centralia residents in the 1970s, including members of Smith’s family, IWW members, classmates, and others who knew him.
Collection contents include Copeland’s research notes as well as reproductions and originals gathered by Copeland from family members and archival repositories of news and magazine clippings, pamphlets, correspondence, and other primary sources, including papers and photographs from Elmer and the Smith family. The collection also contains several scholarly papers and manuscripts, including a draft with notes from Virginia Waddell, Smith’s daughter, of her in-progress biography of her father. Other research materials include correspondence between Copeland and people who knew Smith as well as a large series of oral history interview materials, including correspondence between Copeland and interviewees, paper and digital copies of transcriptions of some of the interviews, and analog and digital audio recordings of many of the interviews.
See the Arrangement Note for a full list of series and subseries. More detailed description of each series is also included in the collection inventory, integrating Tom Copeland’s notes on the collection when available.
Forms part of the Labor Archives of Washington.
No restrictions on access for paper-based materials; however, no user access copies are currently available for audiocassettes or 7" reel. Users may obtain a reproduction of the media for a fee by contacting Special Collections. Access to CD-ROMs can be arranged by making an appointment with the Labor Archives curator prior to viewing. Contact UW Special Collections for more details or to request an appointment.
Harvey O'Connor, 1972 (Biographical sketch of Elmer Smith); Tom Copeland, 2019.
Smith, Elmer,$d1888-1932$vSources; Lawyers$zWashington (State)$vSources; Centralia Massacre, Centralia, Wash., 1919$xHistory$vSources; Industrial Workers of the World$xHistory$vSources; Trials (Murder)$zWashington (State)$xHistory$vSources; Trials (Riots)$zWashington (State)$xHistory$vSources; Riots$zWashington (State)$zCentralia$xHistory$vSources; Labor$zWashington (State)$xHistory$vSources; Labor unions$zWashington (State)$xHistory$vSources; Labor movement$zWashington (State)$xHistory$vSources; Transcripts; Research notes; Newspaper clippings; Manuscripts; Articles; Business correspondence; Facsimiles; Interviews; Ephemera; Centralia Tragedy of 1919; Labor Archives of Washington (University of Washington); Personal Papers/Corporate Records; Labor History
- SUBJECT FILES AND RESEARCH NOTES, 1905-1998; SERIES 1 (Box-folder 1/1, 1/4, 1/12-13, 1/17-18, 1/20, 1/22-28, 1/30-31, 1/35-36, 1/39-40, 1/42, 1/44, 1/45-46, 1/48-50, 2/1-7, 2/11-13, OSVF0203)
  Contains assorted research materials gathered by Tom Copeland, some reproductions from archival repositories as well as originals. Pamphlets located in Series 1 include:
  A Survey of the Workings of the Criminal Syndicalism Law in California
  Let Us Suppose
  Legion Officer and Over Seas Captain Demands Release of Centralia Victims
  Schreckens-Herrschaft in Amerika
  Three New Witnesses of Centralia Tragedy
  Suppressed Evidence in The Centralia Case
  Judicial Murder
  Lumber vs. Labor
  Elmer Smith Pleads of Liberty of Centralia Men
  Equality Before the Law
  Washington's Legal Mockery
  Centralia Case
  Washington's Judicial Mockery
  The Centralia Case by an American Legionnaire
  You Ought to Know
  Speeches by Elmer Smith
  Capt. Edward P. Coll on The Centralia Case
  - Edward Coll: Letters, Pamphlets, and Newspaper, 1928-1929; Subseries A (Box-folder 1/20)
    Includes original notebook of Coll's 1928 handwritten open letter to the American Legion and pamphlets regarding this letter.
  - Elmer Smith, 1905-1990; Subseries B (Box-folder 1/13, 1/23, 1/30, 1/35, 1/50, 2/2, 2/4-6, 2/11-12, OSVF0203)
    - Newspaper Photocopies and Notes on Elmer Smith, 1919-1923 (Box-folder 1/13)
      Includes copies of Centralia Tribune, Chehalis Bee Nugget, the Montesano Vidette, Morning Olympian, New York Call, and New York Times.
    - Notes on Washington Archives Lewis County Criminal Court Files (1915-1939), approximately 1970-1990 (Box-folder 1/23)
    - Elmer Smith History at St. Paul College of Law, approximately 1972 (Box-folder 1/30)
    - Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI) Files on Elmer Smith, 1919-1923 (Box-folder 1/35, 1/50)
    - Virginia Waddell's Unpublished Manuscript Draft on Her Father, Elmer Smith, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 2/2)
      Includes Waddell's notes.
    - Elmer Smith's Correspondence with John Nicholas Beffel of the American Civil Liberties Union, 1924-1932 (Box-folder 2/4)
    - Elmer Smith's Correspondence with Upton Sinclair of Indiana University, 1926-1931 (Box-folder 2/5)
    - People of the State of California v. J.H. Casdorf and Earl Firey: Elmer Smith's Legal Defense Address, 1922 April 10 (Box-folder 2/6)
    - Biographical Sketch of Elmer Smith, approximately 1970 (Box-folder 2/11)
    - Elmer Smith Disbarment Notes and Documents, approximately 1925, 1970-1990 (Box-folder 2/12)
      Contains Copeland's research notes on Elmer Smith's disbarment files held by the Washington State Supreme Court with photocopies of Plaintiff's exhibits of two of Smith's speeches used to disbar him and Defendant brief in support of Smith.
    - Elmer Smith and Football Team Photograph, approximately 1905-1915 (Box OSVF0203)
  - Wesley Everest and Family, 1977-1998; Subseries C (Box-folder 1/17)
    Contains note on Copeland's Pacific Northwest Quarterly research article, "Wesley Everest: IWW Martyr"; letters from brother and others; Evergreen State College magazine "ReView" on Centralia Mural Project featuring Everest; flyer for dedication of the Wesley Everest mural on December 13, 1997; and speech given by Eugene Barnett's daughter, Esther Barnett Goffinet, at mural dedication.
  - Radio Broadcast by Eugene Barnett, approximately 1940; Subseries D (Box-folder 1/44)
    Transcript of radio broadcast in the 1940s on his life and the Centralia case
  - Centralia Tragedy and Trial, 1916-1994; Subseries E (Box-folder 1/4, 1/18, 1/26, 1/36, 1/45-46, 2/3, 2/7)
    - National Archives Military Intelligence Division: Photocopy of Memo to Fay W. Brabson, 1921 August 31 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Centralia Publicity Committee, 1926-1929 (Box-folder 1/18)
    - Evidence for the Centralia Case, 1917-1929 (Box-folder 1/26)
    - "What We Fight For" Theatrical Play about Centralia Case by Park Goist, 1994 (Box-folder 1/36)
    - American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) Documents, 1922-1930 (Box-folder 1/45)
    - Centralia Trial at Montesano, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 1/46)
    - Documentation of the Montesano Trial, 1916-1975 (Box-folder 2/3)
    - Petition to the Acting Secretary of the Centralia Publicity Committee, 1932 May 4 (Box-folder 2/7)
  - Scholarly Papers and Manuscripts, 1960-1991; Subseries F (Box-folder 1/22, 1/25, 1/40)
    - Senior Research Paper, "The Centralia Massacre" by Lewis & Clark College Student, Christine Edmands, approximately 1960 (Box-folder 1/22)
    - "George F. Vanderveer: A Summary of His Noted Cases and His Use of Labor Ideology and Civil Liberties in the Centralia Massacre Trial" by Robert Omberg, 1982 June 1 (Box-folder 1/25)
    - "The Centralia Armistice Day Riot" Nomination to National Register of Historic Places by Robert R. Weyeneth, Ph.D., 1991 (Box-folder 1/40)
      Contains document to nominate various sites in Centralia to the National Register of Historic Places.
  - Newspaper and Magazine Articles, 1915-1974; Subseries G (Box-folder 1/12, 1/24, 1/27-28, 1/31, 1/39, 1/42, 1/49, 2/13)
    Contains photocopies and Copeland's notes, including typed and handwritten transcriptions of some articles.
    - Photocopies and Descriptions of Industrial Worker Magazine, 1920-1932 (Box-folder 1/12)
    - Assorted Newspaper and Journal Articles on Centralia Case and Industrial Workers of the World (IWW), 1919-1925 (Box-folder 1/24)
    - Notes and Newspaper Articles from the Centralia Chronicle, 1915-1974 (Box-folder 1/27)
    - Notes on Industrial Solidarity, 1922-1925 (Box-folder 1/28)
    - Industrialisti Magazine, 1919-1920 (Box-folder 1/31)
      Contains copies of Finnish newspaper with articles covering the Montesano trial.
    - Seattle Union Record, 1919-1924 (Box-folder 1/39)
    - California Newspaper Coverage, 1922 (Box-folder 1/42)
      Contains copies of the Humboldt Times-Standard and the San Francisco Call-Bulletin
    - The Labor Defender Newspaper Coverage of Centralia Leaders, 1927-1933 (Box-folder 1/49)
    - The Farmer-Labor Call Newspaper: Photocopies with Articles on Industrial Workers of the World Trial and Elmer Smith, 1920 October (Box-folder 2/13)
  - Smith Family Papers, 1914-1945; Subseries H (Box-folder 1/1, 1/48, 2/1)
    - Elmer Smith and Family: Letters, Records, and Certificates, approximately 1914-1945 (Box-folder 1/1)
      Includes notes from the Smith family bible indicating birth and death dates of family members, Elmer Smith's death certificate, a copy of a high school essay on ethics written by Smith, his business card, a portion of a poster when he was running for Prosecuting Attorney with his signature, and a Macalester College Debate Society program.
    - Black and White Photo Reproductions of Elmer Smith, his office, Industrial Workers of the World (IWW) Members on Trial, and other Unidentified Individuals, approximately 1915-1925 (Box-folder 1/48)
    - Photographs and Negatives of Elmer Smith, Family, and Acquaintances, approximately 1920 (Box-folder 2/1)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1942-1995; SERIES 2 (Box-folder 1/3, 1/5-6, 1/29, 1/37, 2/14)
  Contains letters to and from Copeland and members of Smith's family and others who knew him, providing information about Smith's life and feedback on Copeland's draft manuscript before and after publishing.
  - Assorted Letters to Tom Copeland about Smith and in Response to Book Publishing, 1972-1994 (Box-folder 2/14)
  - Coll, Edward, 1942-1981 (Box-folder 1/29)
    Correspondence to and from Edward Coll, including conversations with Tom Copeland.
  - Edwards, Herb, 1972-1977 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - O' Connor, Harvey, 1962-1977 (Box-folder 1/37)
  - Smith, Stuart, 1972-1995 (Box-folder 1/5)
    Correspondence between Elmer Smith's son Stuart and Tom Copeland
  - Thompson, Fred, 1983-1986 (Box-folder 1/3)
- ORAL HISTORY INTERVIEW MATERIALS, 1972-1990; SERIES 3 (Box-folder 1/7-11, 1/14-16, 1/19, 1/32-34, 1/38, 1/41, 1/43, 1/47, 2/8-10, 3)
  Copeland conducted a number of interviews with people who knew Elmer Smith on cassette tapes and transcribed them. Later, Elmer Smith's grandson digitized many of the tapes and transcriptions onto two CDs. Most of Copeland's interviews were taped, but some were not and exist only as transcripts or notes.
  Interviewees and relation to Smith:
  Baxter, Sam, Client of Elmer Smith
  Beal, W.H., Classmate of Smith at Macalester
  Beard, Nora, Smith's secretary
  Behrbaum, Orville, Lewis County historian
  Bell, William, Classmate of Smith at Macalester
  Bertagnolli, Frank, IWW member and friend of Elmer Smith
  Boyle, Harry, Classmate of Smith at Macalester
  Burnley, Charlie, Classmate of Smith at Macalester
  Cloud, Lucy Ann, IWW member
  Coll, Edward P. and Aimee Coll (Spouses), American Legionnaire
  Doty, Margaret, Classmate of Smith at Macalester
  Drews, John, Classmate of Smith at Macalester
  Dysart, Lloyd, Centralia lawyer
  Edwards, Herb, IWW member
  Faulkner, Bert, IWW member
  Finan, A., Centralia resident
  Fisk, Wilbur, Classmate of Smith at Macalester
  Fusco, Marie, Centralia resident
  Grundfossen, Iver "Swede", IWW member and logger
  Harmon, Connor, Brother in law of Smith
  Harris, Mabel, Sister in law of Smith
  Heathcote, Hiney, IWW member
  Hodgman, Stanley, Classmate of Smith at Macalester
  Hurd, Loren
  Johnson, John, Classmate of Smith at Macalester
  Killen, Mary, Sister in law of Smith and wife of Smith's Brother Jim
  Lipert, Helen, Centralia resident
  Murphy, Joe, IWW member
  Ruuttila, Julia, Journalist
  Skinner, Grace, Sister in law of Smith
  Skoog, Lawrence
  Smith Nelson, Edna, Sister in law of Smith and wife of Elmer Smith's Brother Bill
  Smith, Stuart, Son of Smith
  Taylor, Elizabeth
  Tripp, Oakley
  Waddell, Virginia, Daughter of Smith
  Willits, Laura, Smith's Wife
  - Transcripts, Notes, and Correspondence, 1972-1990; Subseries A (Box-folder 1/7-11, 1/14-16, 1/19, 1/32-34, 1/38, 1/41, 1/43, 1/47, 2/8)
    - Copeland Interview Tapes Index with Notes from Elmer Smith's Grandson, approximately 1972-1990 (Box-folder 2/8)
    - Baxter, Sam: Notes, 1972-1979 (Box-folder 1/19)
    - Beal, W. H.: Notes, 1972-1979 (Box-folder 1/19)
    - Beard, Nora: Transcript and Correspondence, approximately 1972 (Box-folder 1/47)
    - Behrbaum, Orville: Transcript, 1972-1979 (Box-folder 1/19)
    - Bertagnolli, Frank: Notes from Interview, 1977 June 10 (Box-folder 1/38)
    - Cloud, Lucy Anne: Transcript and Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 1/15)
      Includes photograph of Lucy.
    - Dysart, Lloyd: Notes, 1972-1979 (Box-folder 1/19)
    - Edwards, Herb: Transcript and Correspondence, 1972 October 1 (Box-folder 1/34)
    - Faulkner, Bert: Notes of Phone Conversation, 1972-1979 (Box-folder 1/19)
    - Finan, A.: Notes, 1972-1979 (Box-folder 1/19)
    - Fusco, Maria: Notes, 1972-1979 (Box-folder 1/19)
    - Harmon, Connor: Transcript and Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 1/8)
    - Harris, Mabel: Transcript and Correspondence, 1973-1977 (Box-folder 1/7)
      Includes photograph of Mabel and daughter Dorthy Jean West
    - Heathcote, Hiney: Transcript, 1974 September 29 (Box-folder 1/43)
    - Hurd, Loren: Notes, 1972-1979 (Box-folder 1/19)
    - Killen, Mary: Transcript and Correspondence, 1972-1990 (Box-folder 1/16)
      Includes photograph of Mary.
    - Lipert, Helen: Transcript, 1972-1979 (Box-folder 1/19)
    - Macalester College Classmate, 1972-1974 (Box-folder 1/41)
    - Murphy, Joe: Notes, 1981 July 27 (Box-folder 1/33)
    - Ruuttila, Julia: Transcript and Correspondence, 1972-1990 (Box-folder 1/9)
    - Skinner, Grace: Transcript and Correspondence, 1972-1979 (Box-folder 1/11)
    - Smith Nelson, Edna: Transcript and Correspondence, 1972-1990 (Box-folder 1/32)
    - Waddell, Virginia: Transcript and Correspondence, 1972-1977 (Box-folder 1/10)
    - Willits, Laura: Transcript and Correspondence, 1973-1990 (Box-folder 1/14)
  - Interview Audio Cassette Recordings, 1972-1980; Subseries B (Box-folder 2/10, Box 3)
    - Beard, Nora: Interview at Her Home, 1972 September 17 (Box 3)
      2 tapes
    - Cloud, Lucy Anne, 1972 August 24 (Box 3)
    - Coll, Edward and Amy, 1974 November 6 (Box 3)
    - Edwards, Herb: Interview by Tracy Dalton, 1972 February 12 (Box-folder 2/10)
      7" film reel
    - Edwards, Herb: Interview at his Home, 1972 October 1 (Box 3)
    - Grundfossen, Iver "Swede": Interview at the Home of Edna Smith Nelson, 1972 September 6 (Box 3)
      1 tape
    - Harmon, Connor: Interview at his Home, 1972 September 9 (Box 3)
    - Heathcote, Hiney: Interview at his Home, 1974 September 29 (Box 3)
    - IWW Member (Unidentified Interviewee), approximately 1972-1974 (Box 3)
    - Killen, Mary: Interview at Her Home, 1972 September 30 (Box 3)
    - Ruuttila, Julia: Interview at the Home of Edna Smith Nelson, 1972 September 7 (Box 3)
    - Skinner, Grace: Interview at Extended Services for the Elderly, 1972 October 2 (Box 3)
    - Skinner, Grace: Interview at the Seattle Public Library, 1973 April 21 (Box 3)
    - Skoog, Lawrence, approximately 1972-1974 (Box 3)
    - Smith Nelson, Edna: Interview at Her Home, 1972 September 9; 1980 October 13 (Box 3)
    - Unidentified Interviewee, 1972 September 6 (Box 3)
  - Digital Copies of Interview Transcripts and Recordings, approximately 1972-1990; Subseries C (Box-folder 2/9)
    Contains 2 cd-roms with digital copies of interview transcripts and mp3 files of interview audio recordings for many of the individuals mentioned above. It is possible that these cds contain materials and recordings that only exist in digital form from interviews with individuals not listed above.
    - Beard, Nora
    - Behrbaum, Orville
    - Bell, William
    - Boyle, Harry
    - Burnley, Charlie
    - Cloud, Lucy Ann
    - Coll, Edward and Coll, Aimee
    - Doty, Margaret
    - Drews, John
    - Edwards, Herb
    - Fisk, Wilbur
    - Grundfossen, Iver
    - Harmon, Connor
    - Heathcote, Hiney
    - Hodgman, Stanley
    - Johnson, John
    - Killen, Mary
    - Lipert, Helen
    - Ruuttila, Julia
    - Skinner, Grace
    - Smith Nelson, Edna
    - Smith, Stuart
    - Taylor, Elizabeth
    - Tripp, Oakley
    - Willits, Laura